<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Scholarly Communication Analytics</title>
    <link>https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics</link>
    <atom:link href="https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Based at the Göttingen State and University Library, 
we are analysing data around scholarly communication using open data and tools.
Here, you'll find insights, and examples of our work using R. Particularly, we like
to publish case-studies rapidely showing how to support data-driven workflows and 
decision-making around scholarly communication in libraries using R.
</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Open Access Evidence in Unpaywall</title>
      <dc:creator>Najko Jahn</dc:creator>
      <dc:creator>Anne Hobert</dc:creator>
      <link>https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/posts/unpaywall_evidence</link>
      <description>We investigated more than 31 million scholarly journal articles published between 2008-2018 that are indexed in Unpaywall, a widely used open access discovery tool. Using Google BigQuery and R, we determined over 11,6 million journal articles with open access full-text links in Unpaywall, corresponding to an open access share of 37 %. Our data analysis revealed various open access location and evidence types, as well as large overlaps between them, raising important questions about how to responsibly re-use Unpaywall data in bibliometric research and open access monitoring.</description>
      <guid>https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/posts/unpaywall_evidence</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <media:content url="https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/posts/unpaywall_evidence/distill-preview.png" medium="image" type="image/png" width="1248" height="768"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Scholarly Communication Analytics with R</title>
      <dc:creator>Najko Jahn</dc:creator>
      <link>https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/posts/welcome</link>
      <description>Welcome to our new blog, Scholarly Communication Analytics with R. We hope you enjoy 
reading what we have to say!</description>
      <guid>https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/posts/welcome</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
